Guide to the Rice University Student Organizations records, 1938-1962 UA 039
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University Student Organizations records
1938-1962
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 039
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection consists of the membership and activity records of thirteen Rice Institute student organizations. The earliest date from 1938, and the latest are from 1962.
Biographical / Historical
The thirteen organizations whose records constitute this collection are as follows:
1) Rice Institute chapter of Alpha Phi Omega, a service fraternity made up of men devoted to the oath and laws of the Boy Scouts of America. Records included are from 1949 through 1956.
2) Rice Institute student chapter of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Records included are from 1946-47 through 1958-59.
3) Rice Institute branch of the American Society of Mechanical Engineers. Records included are from 1946-47 through 1961-62.
4) Rice Institute Class of 1961. Records range from Sept. 13, 1960 through May 20, 1962.
5) Rice Institute DeMolay Association. The records are from 1953 through 1956.
6) Rice Institute Engineering Society. The records range from 1946 through 1956.
7) Engineophytes. The records are from 1938 through 1941, when the organization became a chapter of Tau Beta Pi. The records of Tau Beta Pi, Gamma of Texas, from 1941 through 1962 are in a separate folder in this collection.
8) Forensic Society. Records are from 1953 through 1959.
9) Radio Club. Records are from 1946 through 1951.
10) Rice Institute Society of Chemical EDngineers (which became a chapter of the American Institute of Chemical Engineers in 1948). Records range from 1946 through 1957.
11) Sports Car Club. Records are from 1958 through 1960.
12) Tau Beta Pi, Gamma of Texas. This organization is a continuation of Engineophytes, for which there Is a separate folder in this collection. The Tau Beta Pi records range from 1940 through 1961.
13) Virginia Cleveland Literary Society. Records range from 1952 through 1959.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of records of thirteen different student organizations at Rice Institute. The dates of information differ from organization to organization, the earliest being 1938 and the latest, 1962. Financial records are the most common kind of information. For some of the organizations there are membership lists or members' names in receipt book duplicates. Meeting minutes are included for some of the organizations, and some include their constitution and by-laws. Records of a few of the organizations include correspondence concerning speakers for meetings.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research. Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges
Document Types
financial records; documents
Subjects (Corporations)
Rice University
- Series I: Organizations, 164064
  - Alpha Phi Omega, Theta Lambda Chapter. Constitution and by-laws, meeting minutes, and treasurer's records, 1949-56; 152953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers [student branch], Membership lists and treasurers' records, 1946-1962; 152954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - American Society of Mechanical Engineers [student branch], Financial records, 1946-1962; 152955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Class of 1961: Checking account stubs and canceled checks; Final annual financial report for 1960-61; Executive Committee minutes and bimonthly financial reports, 1960-61; Correspondence concerning bank account; Bank records for 1961-62; Financial records from Sept. 13, 1960, through May 20, 1962, 152956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DeMolay Association: Constitution and by-laws; Checkbook stubs and canceled checks, 1954-56; 1953-4 membership list; 1953-54 Treasurer's report, 1953-56; 152957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engineering Society: Ledger and Check registers, 1946-56; 152958 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Engineering Society: Journal recording income and expenditures, 1948-54; 152959 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Engineering Society: Book of receipt duplicates (for members' dues); Membership list, 1954-55; 152962 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Engineering Society Exposition of 1956: ledgers and checkbook stubs, 1953-56; 152963 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Engineophytes: membership list and treasurer's reports, 1938-40; 152964 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Forensic Society: Income and expense records; College Question and Answer Debate Rules; Expense statements of participants in various tournaments; Minutes of Student Senate meeting April 29, 1959; Minutes of Student Senate meeting May 6, 1959, 1953-59; 152965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Radio Club: Suggested procedure for initial organization Constitution (drafts and final); Correspondence relating to affiliating the Rice Institute Radio Club with the Institute of Radio Engineers; Membership lists; Ledger; Account book 1947-50; Receipt book; Check stubs; Meeting minutes; Statement of agreement to disband the club, May 15, 1951, 1946-51; 152966 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Society of Chemical Engineers: Certificate of establishment of chapter of the American Institute of Chemical Engineers,October 8, 1948; Certificates of prizes won by individuals in four contests; Correspondence, mainly concerning arrangements for speakers; Annual reports of activities; Financial reports; Constitution; Meeting minutes, 1946-57; 152967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sports Car Club: Bank account records; Paid invoices, 1958-60; 152968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tau Beta Pi, Gamma of Texas: List of initiates 1917-41; Convention expense report; Treasurer's reports; Receipts for charges paid to meeting locations; Checkbook stubs; Bank account passbooks; Pads of receipt duplicates, 1940-61; 152969 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Cleveland Literary Society: Book of membership and attendance lists and meeting minutes; Constitution; Card granting society members who attended formal dance to have special two o'clock late permission at Jones College, 1952-59; 152970 (Box 3, Folder 5)